{"tossups": [{"question": "This city was where the Selective Buying Campaign was launched. A photo of a serene Walter Gadsden being bitten by a German shepherd was taken in this city. This city's Kelly Ingram Park was where a crowd was attacked with firehoses. This city's police chief Bull Connor was blamed for escalating violence against protestors. For the point, name this site of a decisive spring 1963 civil rights protest, from whose jail Martin Luther King wrote a widely read letter.", "answer": "<b><u>Birmingham</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This decade is when the Lavender List scandal occurred, as well as when Liberal Party leader Jeremy Thorpe was accused of hiring a hitman to murder his lover. At the end of this decade, the headline \"Crisis? What Crisis?\" and the slogan \"Labour Isn't Working\" combined to unseat the Prime Minister who oversaw the \"Winter of Discontent.\" For the point, identify this decade in British politics which ended with James Callaghan losing the PM office to Margaret Thatcher.", "answer": "19<b><u>70</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This queen relied on a secret police known as the \"hermandades\" (<b>pr. AIR-mon-DAHD-ace</b>). The actions of this woman caused the \"moor's last sigh\" when Boabdil was forced to abdicate. This queen of Castile led the conquest of Granada, which, along with her marriage to the king of Aragon, created modern Spain. For the point, name this patron of Christopher Columbus who married Ferdinand.", "answer": "<b><u>Isabella</u></b> I", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The incidence of puerperal fever in patients undergoing this process was greatly decreased when Ignaz Semmelweis (<b>pr. IG-notz SEH-mel-vice</b>) introduced regular hand-washing to hospitals. This process is done \"sympathetically\" by Basque males, and a surgical method for performing this process has risen in frequency by sixty percent since 1996. For the point, name this process which historically has been the cause of death for about 1 in every 2 women.", "answer": "giving <b><u>birth</u></b> [or equivalents]", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {"question": "The tone of this man's major book may be influenced by his own twenty years of exile, which occurred after he surrendered Amphipolis (<b>pr. am-FIP-uh-liss</b>) as a general. This man recorded such momentous speeches as the Melian Dialogue and the Funeral Oration in a book that contains extensive information about the Delian League and Pericles. For the point, name this historian who authored the <em>History of the Peloponnesian War.</em>", "answer": "<b><u>Thucydides</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In the 1990s, the far-right Freedom Party arose in this country. This country was rocked in 1985 by revelations that a former United Nations Secretary-General, who was running for president of this country, had been a member of the Nazi SS. This country was divided into four Allied occupation zones until 1955. For the point, name this country where Kurt Waldheim became president, which is now the second-largest German-speaking country in Europe.", "answer": "<b><u>Austria</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This country's ruling family secured its position at the 1930 Battle of Sabilla, which eliminated a militia known as the \"ikhwan\". This country's five kings since 1953 have all been sons of its founder, who unified the Nejd and the Hejaz following the defeat of Sharif Husayn in 1924. For the point, name this country, which follows Wahhabi Islam and contains Medina and Mecca.", "answer": "<b><u>Saudi Arabia</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Martha Mitchell attempted to reveal her knowledge of this event to her psychiatrist, who did not believe her. This larger event included the firing of Archibald Cox and several men who refused to carry out the firing in the Saturday Night Massacre. W. Mark Felt was revealed in 2005 as Deep Throat, the source who kept <em>Washington Post</em> reporters Bob Woodward and Carl Bernstein aware of this event. For the point, name this break-in that led to President Nixon\u2019s fall.", "answer": "<b><u>Watergate</u></b> scandal (prompt on Saturday Night Massacre before mention)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This company's head, Norio Ohga, was angered when their work on a peripheral for Nintendo's Super Famicom was discarded in favor of a partnership with Phillips. As a result, Ohga ordered Ken Kutaragi to develop a new machine that this company could sell directly. This company launched its first video game console with early titles such as <em>Twisted Metal</em>, <em>Rayman</em>, and <em>Crash Bandicoot</em>. For the point, name this Japanese media giant that makes the Playstation.", "answer": "<b><u>Sony</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Members of this group of people included the Doan Outlaws, who worked as spies in Pennsylvania. The \"United Empire\" faction of these people resettled in Canada. Many black slaves were promised freedom in exchange for becoming these people. Compensation for property confiscated from these people was agreed to in the 1783 Treaty of Paris. For the point, identify these American colonists who sided with the British during the Revolution.", "answer": "<b><u>Loyalist</u></b>s (accept Tories)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "These people were encouraged by the Ottoman Empire to take up arms against the British in World War I via the Khalifat movement. In a 1992 incident, a building used as a place of worship by this religious group was destroyed by hammers after nationalists declared it had been built over the ancient home of Rama in Ayodha. For the point, identify these people who comprise the second-largest religion in India and governed the country during the Mughal era.", "answer": "Indian <b><u>Muslim</u></b>s (accept Sunnis \u2013 do not prompt on Shia or Shiites)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Peter Sweeny and George Barnard were key members of the \"ring\" named for this man. Public opinion turned against him following the Orange Riot, after which he fled to Spain but was recognized thanks to cartoons by Thomas Nast. For the point, name this notoriously corrupt Grand Sachem of Tammany Hall who controlled New York City politics in the 1860s.", "answer": "William \"Boss\" <b><u>Tweed</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Teams of painters were employed to hand-color the red flags in this black-and-white film. An iconic montage from this film shows a woman losing control of a baby carriage, which plummets down the Odessa steps. This film is set during the 1905 revolution and focuses on sailors who discover maggots in their meat. For the point, name this Soviet film created by director Sergei Eisenstein and set aboard a ship named for an advisor to Catherine the Great.", "answer": "<em>The</em> <em><b><u>Battleship Potemkin</u></b></em> [or <em><b><u>Bronenosets Potemkin</u></b></em>]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "Wisconsin's attempt to invalidate this law was thwarted by the Supreme Court in <em>Ableman v.</em> <em>Booth</em>. This act was proposed after the Supreme Court ruling in <em>Prigg v. Pennsylvania</em>, which partially upheld the \"personal liberty laws.\" This act mandated that local authorities cooperate with the \"bloodhound laws,\" infuriating abolitionist Northerners. For the point, name this component of the Compromise of 1850 which mandated returning escapees to the South.", "answer": "<b><u>Fugitive Slave Act</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>Compromise of 1850</u></b> until it is read]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Florentine workers with the raw form of this good, known as \"carders,\" revolted in the Ciompi (<b>pr. CHOMP-ee</b>) rebellion. An English monopoly on this good was given to the Merchants of the Staple, who exported it to Flanders. Demand for this good led to the enclosure movement and the Highland Clearances, which created more grazing areas. For the point, name this good used to make much medieval clothing, which is derived from sheep.", "answer": "<b><u>wool</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This team won an NCAA title after opponent Chris Webber called a nonexistent timeout, earning a technical foul. In 1982, this team scored a victory over Georgetown when a Fred Brown pass was stolen in the final seconds, and their NCAA final victory was sealed when freshman Michael Jordan sank a jumper. This team was coached at the time by Dean Smith. For the point, name this Chapel Hill-based member of the ACC Tobacco Road rivalry with Duke.", "answer": "University of <b><u>North Carolina</u></b> [or <b><u>UNC</u></b>]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This man suppressed the gymnasium movement by issuing the Karlsbad Decrees following the assassination of August von Kotzebue (<b>pr. KOT-seh-boo</b>). This man engineered a Quadruple Alliance which evolved into the less formal Concert of Europe, and is considered the architect of the peace which lasted until his forced resignation during the Revolutions of 1848. For the point, name this Austrian diplomat who presided over the Congress of Vienna.", "answer": "Prince Klemens von <b><u>Metternich</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This author was sentenced to a katorga (<b>pr. kuh-TOR-guh</b>) for belonging to the politically controversial Petrashevsky Circle, which he used as the basis for his novel <em>The House of the</em> <em>Dead</em>. This author also used a term in a labor camp for the last chapter of his story of Porfiry Petrovich catching the man who attacked Alyona and Lizaveta, who run a pawn shop. For the point, name this Russian author of <em>Crime and Punishment</em>.", "answer": "Fyodor <b><u>Dostoyevsky</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "Immediately after this event, a collective fine of one billion marks was levied and insurance reimbursements were forbidden. This event's pretext was the death of Ernst vom Rath, who was shot to death in Paris by Herschel Grynszpan (<b>pr. GREEN-span</b>). This event was named for the broken glass which littered the streets after shop and synagogue windows were smashed. For the point, identify this 1938 Nazi-organized assault on Jewish institutions in Germany.", "answer": "<b><u>Kristallnacht</u> </b> (accept \u201cNight of Broken Glass\u201d \u2013 do not accept \u201cNight of the long knives\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Parts of this document were publicized by the Subcommittee on Public Buildings and Grounds after Mike Gravel submitted it into the record. This document's publication was ruled Constitutionally protected in <em>New York Times v. U.S.</em> An attempt to discredit the leak of this document included a burglary at the office of Daniel Ellsberg's psychiatrist. For the point, name this record of secret U.S. military activity in Southeast Asia which emerged during the Vietnam War.", "answer": "<b><u>Pentagon Papers</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man's mother Hoelun was abducted by his father Yes\u00fcgei, an event described in the first chapter of a \"secret history\" focusing on his rule. This man promulgated his laws in the Yassa Code and was advised by the strategist Subotai. This man began his military career by recovering his kidnapped fianc\u00e9e Borte (<b>pr. BOR-tay</b>) and left his empire to Ogedei at his death. For the point, name this man who united steppe tribes into the Mongol empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Genghis</u></b> Khan [or <b><u>Chingis</u></b> Khan; or <b><u>Temujin</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man sought to improve the system of Valentin Ha\u00fcy (<b>pr. ah-WEE</b>) by adapting a process for encoding military communications invented by Charles Barbier. His new methods were created using a small awl, which, ironically, was the same item which had blinded him at age three in a leatherworking accident. For the point, name this teacher in France who invented a system of raised-dot printing which enables the blind to read by touch.", "answer": "Louis <b><u>Braille</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man was living in exile in Paris at the same time as the future King Charles II, and took the opportunity to tutor Charles in mathematics. This man used physical analogies to explain society in books such as <em>De Motu</em>\u00b8 and he warned of the \"kingdom of darkness\" and \"war of all against all\" in his magnum opus. For the point, name this philosopher who said that avoiding a \"nasty, brutish, and short\" life in the state of nature justified absolute sovereign power in <em>Leviathan.</em>", "answer": "Thomas <b><u>Hobbes</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "A king of these people, Pachacuti, ordered the building of a place where their \"quipu\" communication was used. These people traced their monarchy to Manco C\u00e1pac, the legendary son of the sun god Inti. These people's political power came to an end when the \"ransom room\" failed to prevent Atahualpa (<b>pr. ah-tah-WAL-puh</b>) from being executed by Francisco Pizarro. For the point, name these people who built sites such as Cuzco and Macchu Picchu in what is now Peru.", "answer": "<b><u>Inca</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This city suffered the most damage from Typhoon Ida of any city in Japan. This city was the subject of a story that took up the entire interior of an issue of <em>The New Yorker</em>, by John Hersey, which commemorates an event also denoted in its Peace Museum. For the point, name this city which was targeted on August 6, 1945 by \"Little Boy\" in history's first nuclear attack.", "answer": "<b><u>Hiroshima</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This composer depicted Sesto's plot to assassinate the Roman Emperor in his history opera <em>The Clemency of Titus</em>. His acquaintance Franz Sussmayr (<b>pr. fronss SOOS-my-err</b>) completed the Requiem mass that he left unfinished on his death. This composer was depicted by Tom Hulce in a 1984 period piece which includes the legend that he was poisoned by his rival, Antonio Salieri. For the point, name this Austrian child prodigy who wrote <em>The Magic Flute.</em>", "answer": "Wolfgang Amadeus <b><u>Mozart</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Members of this movement burned down David Lloyd George's country house. Advocates for this cause were subject to force-feeding and the provisions of the Cat and Mouse Act. A member of this cause was trampled by the king's horse at the 1913 Epsom Derby. The key leader in this movement was Emmeline Pankhurst, and it achieved its goal with the Representation of the People Act 1918. For the point, name this cause which was advocated by \"suffragettes.\"", "answer": "<b><u>vote</u></b>s for <b><u>wome</u></b>n in the United Kingdom [or <b><u>suffragette</u></b> movement until it is read]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During this event, the \"Rani of Jhansi\" became a women's icon. This event was the culmination of four years of unease over Lord Dalhousie's application of the Doctrine of Lapse. Its immediate cause was the new Enfield rifle, which required biting to prepare cartridges, and rumors that either beef or pork fat were used to grease the ammunition. For the point, identify this revolt of indigenous soldiers in the Raj which led to the start of direct British rule in India.", "answer": "<b><u>Sepoy</u></b> Mutiny [or Indian <b><u>Rebellion of 1857</u></b>; or <b><u>Great Indian Rebellion</u></b>; prompt on <b><u>Indian Rebellion</u></b>; or equivalents mentioning any word for an uprising alongside the year <b><u>1857</u> </b>or the word <b><u>Great</u></b>; prompt on partial answer]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Freddie Helms and Bryant Allen were riding with this man prior to the incident which catapulted him to fame. Only Laurence Powell and Stacey Koon were ultimately convicted of crimes against this man, which were caught on video by George Holliday. This man asked \"Can we all get along?\" on television during five days of rioting sparked by the original acquittal in his case. For the point, name this black motorist who was beaten by Los Angeles policemen in 1992.", "answer": "Rodney <b><u>King</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This proposal was denounced as \"a fire bell in the night\" marking \"the knell of the Union\" by an elderly Thomas Jefferson. This law was already moot when it was ruled unconstitutional in the <em>Dred Scott</em> case. This law, engineered by Henry Clay, established a line at 36 degrees, 30 minutes latitude. For the point, name this 1820 Congressional effort, which admitted Maine as a free state in exchange for permitting slavery in the namesake midwestern territory.", "answer": "<b><u>Missouri Compromise</u></b> <b>NHBB C 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bee Round 2 Extra Question \u2013 ONLY READ IF YOU BOTCH A QUESTION EARLIER! </b> Territories established by this man were fought over at the Battle of Ipsus, which ended with his former generals Lysimachus (lie-SIM-uh-kiss) and Seleucus (say-LOO-sis) defeating Antigonus. Ptolemy (TAH-luh-mee) was another of the \"diadochi\" (dye-uh-DOH-kee) or \"successors\" who squabbled over this man's empire following his death at Babylon in 323 BC. For the point, name this victor at the Battle of Gaugamela, a prolific Macedonian-born conqueror.  ANSWER: <b><u>Alexander</u></b> the Great [or <b><u>Alexander</u></b> III of Macedon]", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}